Guide to the Funkhouser family papers, 1786-1941, bulk 1836-1908 RL.10049
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Funkhouser family papers
1786-1941, bulk 1836-1908
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Funkhouser family
RL.10049
6 Linear Feet
The Funkhouser family lived in Virginia with members moving West with the expansion of the Unites States. Other Funkhouser descendants moved into Ohio, Maryland and New Jersey. The collection contains correspondence, diary and other papers, chiefly 1836-1908, of the Funkhouser family of Mount Jackson, Va. including Andrew Funkhouser. Topics discussed include conditions in the West, opposition to slavery, and economic conditions in the U.S. after 1837; Civil War letters discuss camp life of Union and Confederate soldiers and the state of the South. Post-war letters are mainly personal. Includes a diary (1863) kept by G. H. Snapp, a minister of the United Brethren in Christ Church, telling of religious life among soldiers and civilians.
Biographical Note
The Funkhouser family lived in Virginia with members moving West with the expansion of the Unites States. Other Funkhouser descendants moved into Ohio, Maryland and New Jersey. Members of the Funkhouser family were soldiers, lawyers, and farmers.
Collection Overview
The collection contains family letters and business papers of the Funkhouser family, and, after 1910, of the Miller family. Most of the papers prior to 1830 are deeds for land in Philadelphia and Virginia. There are two land patents, one signed by Edmund Randolph, governor of Virginia, to Peter Hoshaur, 1788, and one signed by Joseph Johnson, governor of Virginia, to Andrew Funkhouser, 1851.
From the 1830s there are numerous letters from relatives in Virginia, Ohio, Missouri, Indiana, and Wisconsin describing the move westward, religion, railroads, economic conditions, land speculation, opposition to slavery, commerce, Indians, army forts, legal affairs, stock raising, farming, sickness and health, and the Mormon problem in Missouri. Many of these letters are from Funkhouser's son-in-law, John Kerr, a lawyer and speculator. There are also several wills and estate papers.
Civil War letters include items from R. H. Simpson with directions for his home farm and statements about Walker's and Archer's brigades on Funkhouser's land and the amount of wood they used. There is an account book mentioning Confederate Army purchases; papers relating to a claim against the United States for farm buildings, equipment and products burned or seized by order of General Sheridan; and tax in kind estimates and receipts. A diary of Rev. G. H. Snapp of the United Brethren in Christ Church, a brother-in-law of Andrew's son, Casper, discusses his circuit, revivals, conferences, and chaplains in the army; there are also many letters to Snapp down to 1900.
Other letters are from commission merchants in Winchester, Baltimore, Alexandria, and Washington both before and after the Civil War; price current bulletins from Washington, 1890s; and other business letters. Most of the letters after 1880 are from the children of Casper Funkhouser. There is a related genealogical and biographical sketch. These letters describe Shenandoah Seminary, Dayton, Virginia, 1880-1882; Bonebrake Theological Seminary, Dayton, Ohio; teaching at various places in Ohio, Maryland, Virginia, and New Jersey in the 1880s and 1890s; and family affairs. Papers concerning the family of Edward J. Miller include tax receipts, wheat allotment applications, and condolences on Miller's death.
Printed materials with the collection relate to teaching, insurance, an 1899 civil service examination, and standing orders for a mental hospital. Other business papers include tax receipts for Andrew Funkhouser, 1830-1886; tax receipts on Missouri land, 1850-1880; notes, receipts, and bills. Numerous letters refer to the temperance movement in the United Brethren Church and to Andrew Funkhouser's work as a trustee. In the 1880s there are business papers of the Shenandoah Valley Assembly.
Bound volumes include the roll of shareholders and minutes of the meetings of the Shenandoah Valley Assembly, daybooks, 1847-1861, and a ledger, 1836-1843, of Andrew Funkhouser, a list of the personal property of Jacob R. Funkhouser, 1856, and daybooks of John Bauserman, a merchant of Hawkinstown, Shenandoah County, Virginia.
Provenance
The Funkhouser family papers were purchased by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1952 and 1957.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
United States -- Economic conditions -- to 1865; Antislavery movements -- United States; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Religious aspects; Antislavery movements -- Virginia; Clergy -- Diaries; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives; West (U.S.) -- Description and travel; Shenandoah County (Va.); Mount Jackson (Va.); Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life; Church of the United Brethren in Christ (1800-1889) -- Clergy; Church of the United Brethren in Christ (New Constitution) -- Clergy; Funkhouser, Andrew; Snapp, G.H.; Funkhouser family
- Funkhouser family papers, 1786-1941, bulk 1836-1908
  - Letters, 1786-1842; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1843-1878; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1879-1896; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Letters, 1897-1899; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters, 1900-1936 and undated; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1840s-1860s; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1870s-1890s; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Bills, Receipts, etc., 1900-1940s and undated; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Printed and Miscellaneous material, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Rev. G.H. Snapp Diary and typed copy, 1863 (Box 9)
  - Ledger, 1836-1843 (Volume M:5830)
  - Daybook, 1847-1861 (Volume F:5831)
  - Daybook, 1858-1861 (Volume F:5832)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Volume F:5833)
  - List of personal property of Jacob R. Funkhouser, 1856 (Volume L:5834)